After many years of hiding behind
mystique and illiquidity, private
markets are being forced into the light.
Private equity, private credit, and
private real estate have been sold hard
to investors on the premise that they
offer higher returns with less risk. As
fund managers push for these investments
to become more accessible to retail
investors, I think caution is warranted.
I've always been skeptical of private
assets, and I think my skepticism is
being validated. 2026 has been a wake-up
call for everyone who was convinced that
private assets were special. I'm Ben
Felix, Chief Investment Officer at PWL
Capital, and I'm going to tell you why
what we're seeing in private markets
should not surprise anymore.
Private markets are having an
objectively bad time right now. Some
private equity funds are having trouble
selling their holdings, often resorting
to selling private company shares to
themselves. Well, we'll get into that.
Some private real estate funds can't
sell their underlying real estate assets
to meet investors' demands for liquidity
and are having to gate or lock up their
funds. And private credit funds, many of
which are also gating redemptions, are
realizing that a lot of the loans
they've made might have been a little on
the risky side.
I'm not really surprised to see any of
this, but I think a lot of investors in
private market funds will be. Again,
fund managers have pushed private market
investments relentlessly on the premise
that they offer lower volatility and
higher expected returns than what can be
found in public markets. A compelling
sales pitch, for sure,
but it doesn't smell right, and it never
did.
In this video, I'm going to discuss each
of the major private asset classes,
private equity, private credit, and
private real estate. I'll review what
the evidence says and what is happening
in each asset class right now. But
first, a little context. Private assets
are simply assets like stocks, loans
made to companies, infrastructure
assets, which I'm not going to talk
about, and real estate. And they're
assets that have not been listed on a
public exchange. This means you can't
log into your brokerage account and
trade private assets like you can trade
stocks or REITs or whatever.
It also means that the underlying
companies disclosure requirements are
not as strict. Since they don't trade on
public exchanges, the prices of private
assets are not being set throughout the
day like what we see with publicly
listed stocks, bonds, and REITs, making
them appear the private assets appear
less volatile. Appear is the keyword
there. For decades, private market
investments were largely contained
within the realm of institutional
investors, entities like university
endowments, pension funds, and
not-for-profit reserves, entities with a
lot of capital, extremely long time
horizons, and professional staff. I
would argue, with supporting evidence of
course, that private markets are even
questionable for those types of
investors, but more recently private
assets have been increasingly pushed
onto retail investors, whether they're
asking for them or not. In my day job as
the CIO of a Canadian wealth management
firm, I see these sales pitches all the
time and they're only increasing. The
Ontario Securities Market Regulator is
being pressured to authorize a new class
of mutual funds that can hold higher
risk private assets aimed at retail
investors. Similar things are happening
in the US targeting the retirement
accounts of American families. Even if
you could convince me, and I don't think
you can, but even if you could convince
me that institutions should be investing
in private assets, the case for retail
investors is a lot harder to make. The
underlying assets are illiquid, the fees
are high, and the agreements governing
fees and liquidity are complex.
There is, however, huge incentive to
convince retail investors otherwise.
Retail investors in aggregate have a lot
of money, and the high fees charged by
private market fund managers make them
very attractive for the financial
institutions selling them. This is
especially true in a world where
investors are increasingly adopting
low-cost index funds for their public
market investments, driving down profit
margins for financial firms. Retail
investors are also a huge source of
potential liquidity for anyone currently
invested in private markets who wants to
get out. Liquidity has been a huge
problem for private markets lately, but
we'll get more into that later. This
leads to the potential for adverse
selection where retail investors are
showing up to the party a bit late, and
they're the ones getting saddled with
the illiquid stuff that nobody else
wants to buy. Well, the debate about
retail access to private markets
continues. Current investors in these
funds have been forced to learn that
their private market investments are in
fact quite risky. We've seen private
funds write down the value of their
assets, and we've seen them tell
investors they can't have their money
back right now.
We've even seen some of the biggest
historical proponents of private market
investing, Ivy League educational
endowments, start to dial back their
exposure and to lower their expected
returns for their private market
allocations. Some large wealth
management firms have been aggressively
promoting their private market funds
while criticizing the traditional 60/40
stock bond portfolio. They performed
well for a while while public markets
were volatile, but now those same firms
are facing serious problems. They've had
to write down the value of some of their
private funds by huge amounts, and
they've had to tell investors that they
can't access their own money right now
because the underlying assets are too
illiquid to sell. Classic problem of
private markets. This speaks to one of
the inherent tradeoffs with private
assets. You do get less reported
volatility.
Awesome.
Because the underlying assets are valued
infrequently.
Not so great. But you might access to
your money if the private fund does not
want to be forced to sell its underlying
illiquid assets when you need access to
your money.
Not great. In public markets, you can
pretty easily sell at any time, but
you're subject to market prices when you
sell. It's an interesting question
whether it's worse to live with
volatility, but always have access to
your money, even if your investment has
declined in value, or to be artificially
shielded from volatility while
potentially being denied the option to
sell your investments at a loss.
I don't have the universal answer, but I
would generally prefer it liquidity and
knowing what my investments are actually
worth. Private assets started gaining
popularity following the 2008 financial
crisis, likely at least in part in
response to the traumatic levels of
volatility in publicly listed assets
over that period and the need for
investors to find ways to recover from
the losses they sustained in that market
decline. Private markets were sold as a
less volatile place to invest while
earning potentially higher returns. That
alone, that combination of hey, you can
take less risk and earn higher returns
should be a major red flag, but people
really want to believe that they are not
subject to the economics of risk and
expected return. They want to believe
that they can find something special.
Another big selling point for private
assets has always been Yale's endowment.
Yale had pioneered this strategy and had
earned years of famously high returns in
private markets with the legendary late
David Swensen at the helm.
Other investors have wanted to emulate
that outcome ever since.
Yale certainly did perform well, but
recent analysis has suggested that their
famed 30% annualized returns that a lot
of people used as the backbone for the
argument to go into private markets were
not really returns. They are something
called IRRs, which can be very
misleading. My view has always been that
net of fees and properly benchmarked,
there's nothing special in private
markets. I think this only gets more
true in the realm of retail investors
who generally pay even higher fees than
their institutional counterparts.
This point can be contentious and I do
acknowledge that there's a lot of room
for nuance. There are some good private
market funds, at least after the fact we
can find ones that did perform well.
Just like there are some good
traditional actively managed mutual
funds after the fact. Identifying them
ahead of time is not so easy, but there
are ones that have outperformed and
there are ones that will outperform. But
on balance, when you look at the data,
I'm not convinced that the sales pitch
matches the economic reality for private
assets.
Before we dive deeper, if you haven't
already subscribed to this channel,
please do. I make evidence-based videos
on investing in financial
decision-making, helping you make more
informed financial decisions. Okay,
let's look at each asset class
individually. There's some wild stuff
happening in each one. Private equity
invests in private companies, attempts
to increase the value, and then exit the
investment at a profit. Private equity
has multiple underlying strategies with
the two largest being buyouts and
venture capital. Buyouts, the largest
segment by assets, are where firms
acquire a stake in a larger and more
established private company, often using
a lot of debt. Venture capital invests
in early-stage high-growth companies
with the expectation that a small
percentage of those companies will be
massively successful, while many will
lose money. The private equity
industry's value proposition for
investors rests on two main pillars, in
my view: diversification and
market-beating returns. These are
testable claims. I'm not going to
recount all the research on this topic
right now. I've done that in a past
video, but there are two main takeaways
you should know. First is that net of
fee private equity returns can be
largely replicated using public stocks
selected to match the characteristics of
private equity holdings. Second is that
when you adjust private equity returns
for the fact that private company shares
are not valued every day, there is a
dramatic reduction in any
diversification benefit that may have
been observed with the raw, smoothed
returns. In other words, they're a lot
more volatile than they appear. This is
a concept that has been referred to as
volatility laundering. Just because you
don't see the price change every day
like you do with public stocks, doesn't
mean the asset's value isn't
fluctuating. A private equity fund may
look stable on paper while the
underlying economic risks are exactly
the same as or even worse than public
market equivalents. There's also massive
dispersion in private equity fund
returns, meaning that there is a huge
gap between the best and worst funds,
increasing the penalty for choosing a
bad fund. While private equity has
delivered returns roughly in line with
risk-matched public equity. The asset
class has made private equity fund
managers extremely wealthy. This is not
an eat-the-rich type of comment. Private
equity managers have been able to
generate massive returns before fees.
They're clearly skilled at their craft,
and I have no doubt that they are
brilliant people running these funds.
The problem is that, as economic theory
would predict, they are the ones the
managers of the ones that reap the
benefits of their skill, not the
investors in their funds. Well, the
before-fee returns of private equity
have been huge, the net-of-fee returns
have been in line with public markets.
This is explained by the exceptionally
high fees charged by the managers. These
include both management fees and
performance fees and several other
potential layers of fees that all add up
to around 6%. The fee problem isn't the
only issue plaguing private equity right
now. The current state of private equity
is a lot of funds have been unable to
sell a lot of their underlying holdings,
not to meet investor redemption requests
necessarily, but just to turn over the
holdings in their portfolio at a normal
pace. Usually, private equity companies
want to sell their underlying companies
at a sort of 3-7 year cadence to return
capital to fund investors and make new
investments. The result has not been
falling prices for these unsold
companies, which is probably what we
would see if they were publicly traded,
but in the rise of more creative ways to
get cash into the hands of investors.
One prominent example is continuation
funds. A continuation fund is a fund
that buys portfolio assets from an
existing private equity fund, often
managed by the same manager, to give the
fund liquidity. An increasingly common
investor in continuation funds are
called evergreen funds. Evergreen funds
are semi-liquid vehicles that promise
ease of use for investors and give fund
managers flexible capital, which can be
used to support continuation funds and
make other investments. Evergreen funds
often have lower barriers to entry than
a traditional private equity fund, and
they offer more liquidity, making them
accessible to retail investors. While
they have become an important source of
secondary market capital, they raise a
major concern. The fund manager often
controls both sides of the deal. This
makes the accuracy of the secondary
market valuations a little bit murky and
creates conditions for adverse
selection. I think a reason that
investors can more easily buy into these
evergreen funds is that the manager has
investments in an existing fund nearing
maturity that they have not yet sold.
This creates a structural need for exit
liquidity to pay off the original
investors. Private equity funds ideally
want to exit their investments to an
outside buyer after a few years. Instead
sell the assets to an evergreen fund or
a continuation fund that they also
manage, it may indicate that the manager
struggled to find an external buyer
suggesting that the assets might not be
something that you, the investor in the
evergreen fund, actually want to buy. I
think that there's a risk that you're
buying a lemon that the broader market
would not have touched at that price.
This isn't necessarily always the case,
but that's the problem. You don't know.
They're not market tested valuations in
these transactions. Add on top of this
risk that net of fees, as I mentioned
earlier, the average private equity fund
performs roughly in line with public
market equivalents, and investors in
these evergreen vehicles may be taking
on significant complexity and valuation
risk without being properly compensated
for it. Another way that investors in
private equity funds have gotten around
the difficulties in selling their
holdings is by selling them at pretty
major discounts. Say you have invested
in a private equity fund, but you need
some cash. The fund isn't liquid, but
you can find someone to buy your stakes
at a deep discount. This comes with its
own problem that's emerged known as NAV
squeezing. We've seen this issue surface
recently with universities that hold
private equity investments in their
endowments like Yale and Harvard.
Universities, Yale in particular as I
mentioned earlier, were among the
earliest adopters of private equity
funds as their long time horizons made
them well suited to lock up capital in
illiquid assets in exchange for what
they hoped for and and maybe in some
cases generally got
uh higher expected returns. Even if this
strategy was historically effective in a
slow market with high interest rates and
private equity funds taking longer than
usual to return capital, universities
have been forced to sell their stakes
sooner than planned to free up cash and
fund their operations. This has been
true for other investors, too.
To do this, universities like Harvard
and Yale have been selling parts of
their private equity portfolios to
secondary buyers at discounts averaging
around 11% at least in this data.
This discount is a markdown from the
position's net asset value or NAV, which
is what the fund manager is saying that
the assets are worth.
What gets crazy here, though, is that
the secondary market buyers can put the
purchase price on their own books and
immediately mark it back up to the
original NAV. So, if Harvard sells a
$100 million stake in a private equity
fund at a at an 11% discount as the
average shows, the secondary market
buyer can purchase that stake for $89
million,
but then immediately mark it back up to
$100 million because that's still the
fund's initial net asset value. This is
allowed in the accounting rules. So,
they paid less for it,
and it's usually a private equity fund
that is buying these fund stakes like a
fund of funds. On paper, the purchase
has generated an immediate 11% return
for the purchasing fund, even though
nothing about the underlying value of
the companies or fund stakes has
changed. This process has become
increasingly common with secondary
market sales increasing 45% to $162
billion last year, and it could be seen
as a win-win for those involved in the
transaction. Universities free up some
capital, often still more than they paid
for the initial investment in the fund,
and the secondary buyer of the fund
stakes reports a massive return for
their fund.
Recently, some fund managers have even
adapted their fee structure to
capitalize on this. Fund manager
Hamilton Lane has updated their fee
structure to collect performance fees
based on the unrealized gains rather
than waiting until a company is actually
sold as would usually be the case.
Hamilton Lane reportedly took in $58
million in incentive fees shortly after
changing its fee structure, which they
may not have seen for years if ever
under the old fee rules. Again, if this
whole thing smells a little bit fishy, I
think you've got a good nose. Some
people have speculated that this change
in fee rules is because the fund manager
themselves may suspect that these higher
paper valuations may not last.
And the mere presence of the discount
when they buy the fund stakes lends some
credence to this suspicion. It raises
the question of whether the fund was
ever worth the $100 million
to begin with. When retail investors are
sold and believe the idea that private
equity funds can actually generate these
returns for them, that becomes a
problem. You may hold an investment
showing strong official paper returns on
your monthly statements, but when you
actually need liquidity, you discover
that you're either unable to access your
funds or that you need to sell your fund
stakes at a deep discount. Another
current concern is the private equity
industry's heavy exposure to software
companies where private equity has
concentrated a huge portion of its deals
over the past decade. The private equity
playbook of borrowing a bunch of money
to buy a successful SaaS business and
then improving it a bit for an exit a
few years later works when the economy
is good and the demand for software is
high, but it kind of falls apart when
corporate spending is strained and
something like AI threatens to disrupt
the SaaS revenue model altogether.
This exposure is now affecting other
parts of the private market because
who's private equity borrowing from to
get leverage for these software buyouts?
In many cases, private credit. Private
credit consists of loans to private
companies, kind of like bonds except the
loans are not publicly traded and
they're created by non-bank entities
like private credit funds or business
development companies, BDCs for short.
We're going to talk more about them in a
minute. These funds raise money from
investors and make direct loans, often
with flexible terms and covenants, to
private companies. These loans, by their
nature, by being loans to private
companies, are risky. Like private
equity, private credit funds will not
have their assets marked to market
daily. This allows them to appear low
risk and if the value of their
underlying assets, of the underlying
loans would be fluctuating wildly in the
public markets. And there's an
interesting way where we can see that
that's actually what's happening and and
I'll talk about that in a sec. Similar
to private equity, when the returns on
private credit funds are properly
evaluated against risk appropriate
benchmarks, I don't think there's
anything special there. One important
point is that similar to publicly traded
high yield bonds, private loans often
share return characteristics with
riskier stocks. While private credit has
seen enormous growth, the assets has
recently started to see investors
wanting their money back. But due to the
illiquidity in the underlying loans,
some private credit funds have had to
gate redemptions. Think about this as an
investor. You put your money in a
private credit fund to try to get some
nice juicy yield which was marketed to
you super hard in whatever app you're
using or whatever financial advisor you
were talking to,
you start to feel a little bit uneasy
for whatever reason about the underlying
assets or about the economy, about your
job. So you ask for your money back. The
problem is that people usually start to
feel uneasy about those things around
the same time. So while everyone wants
their money back, the private credit
fund has to say no. Now, to be clear,
this is not private credit funds being
evil. This is a feature, not a bug, at
least if you are the private credit
fund. Private loans are typically
long-term loans that are not expected to
be or designed to be liquid. Investors
in these funds should understand that
going in, but I think that's easier said
than done especially in retail as we
have seen recently. In some cases, gated
funds can be locked up for years.
Publicly listed BDCs on the other hand
offer a fascinating contrast to unlisted
BDCs or private credit funds. Rather
than gating, they feel the full force of
the markets assessment of the value of
their underlying loans. Take the FS KKR
Capital Corporation as one example. It
reported an increase in troubled loans
and lower investment income, and the
market responded swiftly. Again, this is
publicly traded. The fund is down
significantly for the 12 months ending
February 27th. Another BDC, MidCap
Financial Investment Corp, has similarly
marked down some of its loans and been
recognized by the public market for
their honesty about their disclosures,
again with the price of that BDC
dropping significantly. If nothing else,
that should indicate how much risk
private credit funds, unlisted private
credit funds, where you don't get to see
the the valua- valuations fluctuating in
the public market, it should really
indicate how much risk they're actually
taking.
Again, these are very similar things.
One's publicly listed, one's not.
When you have risky underlying assets,
you're either going to get volatility,
or if you say, "I don't want to see the
volatility, so I'm going to get invest
in a private fund," then you're going to
get illiquidity when public markets get
volatile. One of the problems with
illiquidity is that you have to own
assets that you know kind of stink. Once
the fund manager says, "No, you can't
have your your money back," that's
usually at a time when the underlying
are stressed, are struggling, which is
why they can't be sold. And you have to
then continue to pay fees on those
stinky assets to to own them while while
you're not able to sell. The other crazy
thing that's happening in private
credit, where firms are getting
increasingly creative for ways to come
up with with cash, with liquidity for
the underlying funds,
uh is they're turning to some pretty
interesting shenanigans with insurance
companies uh to to meet their liquidity.
So, life insurance companies have
traditionally kept their massive cash
reserves in stable, conservative
investments, like whatever, stocks and
bonds, things like that.
Diversified portfolios. They're they're
kind of the classic uh conservative
institutional investor. Private equity
firms are now buying insurance
companies, moving significant portions
of their portfolio into private credit
for its higher yield. And insurance
companies, so they they take in
insurance premiums, they have to be able
to pay out uh the death benefit or
disability benefit or whatever when
someone dies or becomes disabled, but in
the interim, they can invest those the
the excess premiums that they don't need
to to run the business, and they get to
keep the difference between what they
earn on their investments and what they
pay out to policy holders. That's a
simplification, but it's it's basically
like that.
So, the the recent playbook that has
emerged is that private equity buys an
insurance company,
and then instead of maintaining the
typically conservative investment
portfolio, they stuff its portfolio with
private credit funds,
often from lenders that are owned by the
same private equity firm that owns the
that now owns the insurer. Kind of
crazy, and this process is creating a
closed loop of risk with hopefully
obvious potential repercussions if the
private loans go sour. The issues
rattling private equity and private
credit are becoming increasingly clear
to the market. Major publicly listed
players in these asset classes, that is
publicly listed companies who sell and
manage private equity and private credit
funds, have seen their share prices get
obliterated in recent history as the
underlying risks in what they have been
selling are increasingly pushed into the
light. The last asset I'll cover is
private real estate. Private real estate
funds directly own real estate assets
like apartment buildings, office towers,
and shopping malls. They can have
various strategies, but the general idea
of owning real buildings inside of a
private fund is consistent across this
asset class. They're often not unlike a
publicly traded REIT, except that the
private funds don't trade on the stock
market, similar to what we talked about
with private equity and private credit.
Also, like private equity and private
credit, some private real estate funds
in Canada have struggled with liquidity.
This is not super surprising. The
Canadian real estate market has
experienced its worst real price decline
going back to 1975. Public residential
REITs have taken a beating, and private
fund managers, understandably, don't
want to be forced to sell assets that
have declined in price. That's fine, and
it's why their contracts with their
investors allow them to gate their funds
when too many people are asking for
liquidity at the same time.
In the midst of the liquidity crunch for
many private Canadian real estate funds,
some are considering going public as a
source of liquidity. Being public means
that investors can buy and sell their
shares on the open market without the
fund needing to sell its underlying
assets, but it also exposes the value of
the funds units to market prices. While
these funds consider going public,
they've halted redemptions for current
investors.
I can't tell you what will happen with
these IPOs, but I can tell you what
happened in similar situations in the
US. In November of last year, FS
Specialty Lending Fund listed on the New
York Stock Exchange at a net asset value
of $18.67
a share. On the end of its first day on
the market, it closed at $14. In
December, Blue Rock's Total Income Plus
Real Estate Fund began trading on the
New York Stock Exchange with a stated
NAV of $24.36
a share. At close, the fund was trading
at a market price of $14.70
a share, nearly a 40% drawdown from the
beginning of the day. It's kind of
funny, but funny's not the right word
because there are real investors who are
in difficult situations because because
of this, but these funds are sold as
protection against stock market or or
public market volatility, but they often
take huge hits once they themselves are
exposed to genuine price discovery in
the market. The risk was still there,
they just weren't telling you about it
or showing it to you. An important
question then in private real estate is
whether private real estate funds are
adding anything special that cannot be
found in a liquid public REIT. A 2018
paper finds that public REITs behave a
lot like a portfolio of 60% small value
stocks and 40% long-term high-yield
bonds, and that private REITs behave
almost exactly the same way when a
valuation lag is accounted for. In other
words, the stock and bond factors that
explain public REIT returns also fully
explain private real estate returns. A
2019 paper similarly finds that when
adjusted for the different leverage and
sector composition of public and private
real estate indices, there's no special
return premium in private real estate.
Again, this does not mean that there are
no good private real estate funds. I'm
sure they're out there. Private markets
have been sold to investors as a way to
increase their expected returns without
increasing and maybe even decreasing the
amount of risk they are taking relative
to public markets. Recent red flags in
private equity, credit, and real estate
have shown that these assets are at
least as risky as their public
counterparts and maybe hiding additional
layers of risk due to high fees,
illiquidity, and less scrutiny in how
assets are valued. I'm glad that my firm
did not jump headfirst into the space
when it started getting pushed hard into
retail channels and I hope retail
investors will approach these assets
carefully as they continue to be
promoted. If you want to know more about
PWL's super boring investing philosophy,
you can click here. Or if you'd like to
learn about the research on private
equity, you can click here. Stay safe
out there.